Guide to the Ralph Emerson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ralph Emerson papers
1808-1811
MS 199
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers are comprised of typescript copies of writings of Ralph Emerson, the originals of which are held in the archives of Beloit College. The papers date from Emerson's matriculation at Yale College where he was the valedictorian of the class of 1811. The collection includes debates, a diary, notes from lectures of Timothy Dwight, correspondence, speeches, essays and other short writings.
Emerson, Ralph, 1787-1863
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert K. Richardson, 1937.
Biographical / Historical
Ralph Emerson was born in Hollis, New Hampshire, on August 18, 1787. He graduated from Yale College in 1811 and received a Doctor of Divinity degree from the school in 1830. He served as Pastor of the Congregational Church in Norwalk, Connecticut from 1816 to 1829 and as a professor at Andover Theological Seminary from 1829 to 1854. Emerson died in Rockport, Illinois on May 26, 1863.
Scope and Contents
The papers are comprised of typescript copies of writings of Ralph Emerson, the originals of which are held in the archives of Beloit College. The papers date from Emerson's matriculation at Yale College where he was the valedictorian of the class of 1811. The collection includes debates, a diary, notes from lectures of Timothy Dwight, correspondence, speeches, essays and other short writings.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
College prose, American -- Connecticut -- New Haven; College students -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817; Emerson, Ralph, 1787-1863; Yale University -- Student life
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The papers are comprised of typescript copies of original manuscript writings of Ralph Emerson, valedictorian of the Yale College Class of 1811. Emerson wrote the papers during his years at Yale and they document student academic life at the beginning of the nineteenth century. The collection has been maintained in the order in which it was received and folder titles are the titles of the writings.
  - "Ten Disputes of Ralph Emerson in Yale College" [Junior year], 1809-1810 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1808-1811 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Dr. Dwight's Remarks upon the Assembly's Catechism" [Emerson's notes], 1810-1811 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Valedictory oration, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Dr. Dwight's Decisions" [Emerson's notes], 1810-1811 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Senior Debates of Ralph Emerson in Yale College", 1810-1811 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "On Emulation", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Possunt quia posse videntur. Vir", undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "A Dissertation on the Pleasures of Anticipation, delivered in the Chapel", 1810 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "An account of Milvander till his unhappy connection with Myranda" [narrative composition], 1809 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "On Profanity: 'Swear not at all'", 1808 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Composition: a letter", 1809 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "On Slavery", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)